Rhiannon: Person-centred care with
Children and young people, means that they
are at the centre of the support offered.
That support includes choice and is
holistic and specifically tailored to
the young person’s needs and wishes.
In the past, people were expected
to fit in with the routines and
practices that health and social
services felt were most appropriate.
But in order to be person-centred,
services have had to change to be
more flexible to meet individual needs
in a manner that is best for them.
Leah: Being compassionate, thinking about
things from the person’s point of view
and being respectful are all important.
This might be shown through sharing
decisions with a young person
and their family and helping
them to manage their health.
It is as much about the way
professionals and individuals think
about care and their relationships,
then the actual services available.
Rhiannon: There are also different ways
this partnership can work, such as on
a one-to-one basis, where children and
young people take part in decisions about
their health and care directly, or on a
collective group basis, whereby groups
are involved in decisions about the design
and delivery of person centred services.
The underlying philosophy is the
same, it is all about doing things
with people, rather than ‘to’ them.
Leah: Including young people in the
decision making around their mental
health care leads to better involvement
and engagement and can help in
creating a successful recovery model.